{
  "reference_number": "9497",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "There is no time to delay any decisions as we are already several decades late to start meaningful change."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We need a holistic view on all climate affecting gases, materials and actions/inactions. This includes looking at short term / long term\n effects and a targeted approach. It also has to include whole life cycle analysis including emissions created outside of New Zealand."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New forest planting can only be taken into account if it is done for primary forests, not for commercial forestry as this provides only\n\n temporary carbon capture and will result in additional emissions further down the line. Reduction has to be achieved through a\n behavioural shift (real car sharing, effective and interconnected public transport, walking/cycling, away from consumerism, not relying\n\n on technology to help us)."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Or only to reduce emissions faster."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "It should not be able to reduce the target, only to progress faster."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "See Note 6. The biggest exceptional circumstance of out time is Climate Change. We won't have an economy down the line if we\n\ndon't address CC."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "To reduce cumulative emissions sufficiently to avoid dangerous climate change, the steepest cuts must occur in the first 10 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Agriculture: life stock density, monoculture, erosion, water quality (down to collector creeks), nitrates, chemicals use Transportation:\ntrucks, single occupancy motor vehicles, public transport, active modes of transport, share schemes Consumers/retail: single use\n\nitems, packaging, container deposit , stuartship"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We as a nation have to make significant changes in all areas of our lifes. This issue can't be solved by any one group: industry,\n\ntransport, individuals. We're in it together. The biggest thing in my mind is a cultural shift to less consumerism (in all its forms) and\nmore community engagement and empathy. Only such a shift in individuals can successfully change behaviour of business and\n\nIndustrie. Governments can support such a culture shift through education, incentives and regulation/legislation."
    }
  ]
}
